<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[The dreadfull day dolorous to the wicked. In two sermons. By William Leigh.]</title>
            <author>Leigh, William, 1550-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14434</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838974</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176871</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248556930</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 15423.5</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S103217</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99838974e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14434)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176871)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 715:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[The dreadfull day dolorous to the wicked. In two sermons. By William Leigh.]</title>
                  <author>Leigh, William, 1550-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 130 [i.e. 126]+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>T. Creede,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title and imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Pages missing and misnumbered; text is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 25423b on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page and all following page 130 lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Judgment Day --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:176871:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176871:1"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, SYR <hi>Iames Altome</hi> Knight, one of the Barons of the Exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>equer, and sir <hi>Edward Phillips</hi> Knight, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Sergiant at Lawe, Iudges for the Northeren Circuit. Grace be multiplied in this life, and happines in the world to <hi>come.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume be little, and the leaues but fewe, I here offer, either to expresse the
<pb facs="tcp:176871:2"/>dutie I owe, or to vnfolde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie project worthy your iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious eye and censure: yet for that the subiect in some sort is sutable to your place, and calling, Pardon me in your patience, if I craue pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage. The booke <hi>Iohn</hi> took from the Angels hand, was but a little one, yet was it passionate in the eating, sweet in the mouth, and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the bellie; voyces, roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, &amp; thunderings went with it, and a powerfull speech bound with a sacred oath, that <hi>Time</hi> should be no more; The vision was
<pb facs="tcp:176871:2"/>for an appointed time, and now is the time. For iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is at our doores, and that which deuoureth all, with mortalitie, is euē now ready to be swallowed vp it self with Aeternitie, for time shall bee no more: <hi>Est dies, &amp; Deus vltionis;</hi> There is a day, and a God of reuenge. A day of doome, and a God of Iudgement; A day of death, and a day of deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from death &amp; doome. <hi>Inde venturus,</hi> shall ende all time in this world, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne Eternitie in a better; when all iudgement shalbe
<pb facs="tcp:176871:3"/>deuolued into the hands of Christ, whose fanne is in his handes, now readie to win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowe the Chaffe from the Wheate, with an eternall doome of Life for the one, and of Death for the other. Spare mee to speake of that great Day, and when I haue done, pardon my boldnesse, if I presse it as a president for Iudges of the Earth to iudge, and to be iudged by: next vnder God &amp; the King, you doe worthilie possesse one of the greatest Circuits of Iustice within the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; &amp; with what feare
<pb facs="tcp:176871:3"/>of God, loyaltie to your Prince, loue of the subiect, and integritie towardes all, I appeale to the conscience of those Countries, where it is both dulie seene, and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie felte; I say felt, in the sweet temper of mercie and iudgement, euer cancelling the rigour of the Law, with the mildnes of the Gospell, and beating backe the swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of <hi>Iordan,</hi> that runneth roughly, with the sweet rū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning waters of <hi>Sylo,</hi> that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth softly by <hi>Syon:</hi> Til I leaue to liue, I shall neuer forget your religious care at <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:176871:4"/>ouer the dead, (I meane the poor condemned priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, then ready to die by the doome of <hi>Iustice</hi>) how they might be wrought willing to leaue this miserable <hi>world,</hi> and be prepared for a better.</p>
            <p>And finding in your right iudgements, (being rightlie resolued) that it could neuer be but vpō the sight of their sinnes, and feeling of their Sauiour; your holie resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was, they should bee brought to publique praier, and Preaching, in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, the day before their <hi>executiō,</hi> wher honored with
<pb facs="tcp:176871:4"/>your presence, &amp; sanctified with your Prayers, <hi>w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               </hi> much sweet Baulme of that great congregation, powred vpon their heades, to burie them withall: It was strange to see, how <hi>Dauids</hi> harp abated <hi>Saules</hi> rage: I meane how that heauēly harmony quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the desperate, confessing their sinnes, and longing for the houre of their dissoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with desire to be loosed, and to be with <hi>Christ,</hi> there to walke, in the land of the liuing. They mooued your L: yet further, that this their Faith might bee confirmed,
<pb facs="tcp:176871:5"/>and sealed vp, with the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of <hi>Christ</hi> his blessed death &amp; passion, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing graunted by you, &amp; cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated by vs, a little before their going to Execution, I appeale to the Sheriffe of the Countrie, and at least to a thousand lookers on, how cheerfullie they died, seuen vpon the tree, and one at the stake: truly confessing their sinnes to God, in the sight of men and Angells, with an assured hope of pardon, in, and through the bloudshed of <hi>Christ,</hi> their alone sauiour, &amp; redeemer; not doubting,
<pb facs="tcp:176871:5"/>but vpon the dissolution, as their body must to the earth from whence they came, so their soules should immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately passe to God, that gaue them, there to be tyed, as in the bundle of the liuing.</p>
            <p>It were to be wished this memorable acte of yours, might be cōtinued &amp; made exēplarie, to the rest of your Ranke, in their seuerall Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuits, you may take &amp; leaue, as you see occasion; Yet if you please, after iudgement whilst they yet liue, to lappe your dead in such <hi>Syndon,</hi> it wil be honorable to you, as
<pb facs="tcp:176871:6"/>it was to <hi>Ioseph</hi> of <hi>Arimathia,</hi> and <hi>Nicodemus;</hi> when they for the Head, &amp; you for the members, are so charitablie deuoted: sith he that sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, &amp; they that are sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, are both one.</p>
            <p>It was vsuall with the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giptians,</hi> in their solēne feasts, to drinke the last draught in a dead mans skull: thereby, in the height of their solace, to put them in mind of their mortalitie: I haue said, <hi>Ye are Gods,</hi> that's your prayse: yet <hi>must ye die like men,</hi> that's your check. It will not be amisse therefore, as you slide from
<pb facs="tcp:176871:6"/>your thrones of Honour, to look vpon the dust of those yee haue condemned, &amp; to tender the saluation of those poore soules, whose bodyes you haue rēdred vnto death, not doubting <hi>Quin patibulo ad Polum patent jis aditus:</hi> I meane to all such as shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme a bad life, with a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent death: and say, in the patience of their soules, bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed is the tree whereon righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes hangeth, wee are iustly punished, &amp; haue sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but hee that saueth vs, hath done nothing amisse.</p>
            <p>To this GOD and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,
<pb facs="tcp:176871:7"/>I leaue you both, with all your religious endeuors, pressing your affections to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards mee, no further, but as in dutie and true deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I shall merit the same.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your VVorships, much bounden, VV. Leigh.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:176871:7"/>
            <head>THE DREAD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVLL DAY.</head>
            <head type="sub">The first Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Hebrewes. 9. vers. 27.28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="27">27. And as it is appointed vnto men that they shall once die, and after that commeth the iudgement.</p>
                  <p n="28">28. So Christ was once offered to take away the sinnes of manie, and vnto them that looke for him, shall he appeare the second time, without sin vnto saluatiō.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Scripture which I haue read issuing from the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of life, being pure as gold, and cleare as Christall, doth discouer
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:176871:8"/>vnto vs, a threefold day-dawning out of the bright cloud of the Lords decree and determined counsell ouer all flesh.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>One is the daie of death in these</hi> words. <hi>It is appointed vnto all men that they shall once die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Another is, the daie of doome, out of these words; <hi>And after that commeth iudgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 The third and last is, the day of deliuerāce frō both by Christ, out of these words; <hi>So Christ was once offered to take away the sinnes of many, &amp; vnto them that looke for him, he shal appeare the second time, without sinne vnto saluation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The day of death, it killeth all, and bringeth to the graue.</p>
            <p>The day of doome, it raiseth all, and bringeth vnto iudgement.</p>
            <p>The day of deliuerie, it sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all, and destinateth for euer,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:176871:8"/>the good to the resurrection of saluation, whither God bring vs: And the euill to the resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of condemnation, from which the Lord deliuer vs.</p>
            <p>Or thus, death is the Empresse of this world, it seazeth vpon all.</p>
            <p>Iudgment hath the command of another world; it sommoneth all: Christ hath the soueraigntie of both worlds, he sentenceth all, irreuocable is his doome, and there lies no appeale from it.</p>
            <p>Pardō me my brethrē, if I spare to speake of death, hauing hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore spent my spirits &amp; strēgth on that subiect, whē with the poore <hi>Gadaren</hi> oftē I haunted the graues of your dead in their seuerall Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls, &amp; wounded my self with the stones of their sepulchers.</p>
            <p>Two sermons are published to the world, I pray God they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176871:9"/>may be profitable, it was the best perfume I had for the liuing, and finest Syndon, I could prouide for the dead.</p>
            <p>So discharged of death as I haue said, heare me in your won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted patience, whilest I discouer vnto you the day of doome, and that other of our deliuerance by Christ, I say deliuerance from darke <hi>Egipt,</hi> into bright <hi>Gosan:</hi> from great <hi>Sodome,</hi> into litle <hi>Soar:</hi> from the miserie of this life, to the mercie of a better: from death here, to life there: and as it is in my text, from sinne, to saluation, to all such as looke and long for Christ his second comming.</p>
            <p>To the due consideration whereof, and the rather to stir vp your due deuotion, and like pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration both of lampe &amp; light, against that great day, giue me
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:176871:9"/>leaue with milde <hi>Moses,</hi> to charge all men, that their thoughts are extrauagāt, without sense or fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of that fearefull fire. O that men were wise (saith he) then would they vnderstand this,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.29.</note> then would they consider their latter end.</p>
            <p>As, and if he should say, that which another hath well said from his spirit &amp; passion: O that men were wife, then would they vnderstand things past, things present, things to come: things past with griefe, things present with shame: things to come with feare, things past as the euill we haue committed: the good we haue omitted, and the time we haue lost, all past, and yet we grieue not.</p>
            <p>Things present, as shortnes of life, difficultie of saluation, &amp; the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176871:10"/>small number of the saued, all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, and yet we shame not.</p>
            <p>Things to come, as death, thē which theres nothing more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable: Iudgement, then which theres nothing more terrible: &amp; the paines of hell, then which there is nothing more intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and all to come, and yet we feare not.</p>
            <p>The reason of all this defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is rendred by <hi>Moses</hi> in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent 28. verse, we are a Nation (saith he) (we are a world say we voyd of counsell, neither is there any vnderstanding in vs, we feele no mercy, we feare no iudgmēt, he hath spent his plagues vpon vs, he hath shot his arrowes at vs, tipped with gall and sorrow, as famine, sword, and pestilence, &amp; yet we are secure in our sinnes, we are frozen in our dregges, we
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176871:10"/>melt not, what would we haue God to do, shall he come in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie still, &amp; not in iudgment? shall he in his loue chearish vs? and not in his wrath rebuke vs? What will we haue God to doe?</p>
            <p>The Gospell of our Christ hath run floudwise into the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motest parts of this world, and thousand of yeares haue enioyed our Christ with his solemne feasts, Sacraments and Sabboths, now if we sinne willingly after we haue receiued and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged that truth, there remaines no more sacrifice for sinnes as the Apostle saith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.26.</note> but a dreadfull loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for of iudgement, and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent fire which shall deuour the aduersaries. Fire, I say fire, euen that fire wherewith <hi>Moses</hi> threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the <hi>Israel</hi> of <hi>Iuda,</hi> and in them the <hi>Israel</hi> of all the world, for the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:176871:11"/>like contempt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deuter.</hi> 32.22.</note> fire is kindled in my wrath, and shall burne into the bottome of hell, &amp; shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume the earth, with her increase, and set on fire the foundations of the mountaines, <hi>Et lugenda dei iudicia in delinquentes,</hi> as one saith; That there shall be a fire is much, that this fire shall be kindled is more, but that it shall be kindled in the wrath of God, is most of al: the flame whereof shall burne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bottome of hell, consume the earth, and the foundations of the mountaines.</p>
            <p>Now of this fearefull &amp; finall fire must I speake if God will, and therefore flie out my voyce, and be strōg my spirit, to speake with passion what the iudgment shall be.</p>
            <p>When Lord <hi>Aeneas</hi> should relate vnto <hi>Dido,</hi> Queene of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:176871:11"/>the lamentable siege and sacking of <hi>Troy,</hi> he began his speech with this passion, <hi>Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Regina iubes renouare dolorem, troian as vt opes &amp; lamentabile reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, eruerint Danaj.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A dolefull wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke me to renue ô queene thou doest constraine, to tell how Greeks the Troyan wealth, and lamentable raigne, did ouerthrowe.</p>
            <p>A better spirit bids me speake of the siege and sacking of this world, whereof <hi>Troy</hi> was but a drop to the great Ocean, and not to be destroyed by the Grecian Lords, but by the great God of heauē: how can I thē tell of that without mourning? How can you heare thereof, without moane, being a worke of woe and wonder, a worke of feare and fire, so is the last iudgement.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:176871:12"/>
            <p>Of which iudgement, I pray you consider with me these two things out of my text.</p>
            <p n="1">1 First, that iudgement shall come, for so is it here said. <hi>After death commeth ïudgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, for what cause this iudgment shall come, to wit, to cleare the godly, &amp; condemne the wicked.</p>
            <p>For so it is here said; <hi>To thē that looke for him, he shall appeare the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time without sinne vnto salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Implying thereby, that to such as looke not for him, he shall then come to their iust condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>Now for the former, these questions may be moued.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Whether there shall be any iudgement?</p>
            <p n="2">2 Who shall be iudge?</p>
            <p n="3">3 By what proces, examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:176871:12"/>and execution it shalbe effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?</p>
            <p n="4">4 What shalbe the precedent signes of such iudgement?</p>
            <p>Of these in order as the time will permit, hoping you will heare with vnwearied diligence what the Lord will bring to passe in so great a wonder.</p>
            <p>For that which is moued in the first place whether there shall be any iudgment or no,
<note place="margin">That there shall be a Iudgment.</note> the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion is necessarie, because the scripture hath foretold that there should come mockers in the last daies, which wil walke after their lusts, and say,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Peter.</hi> 3.3.4.</note>
               <hi>Where is the promises of his comming? for since the fathers died, all things continue alike from the beginning of the creation.</hi> Trees growe, riuers flowe, sunne shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, moone and starres send out their light as of old, seedtime and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:176871:13"/>haruest fall out in their due sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and winter &amp; s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmer saile vs not of their appointed times: men are mortall, &amp; yet liue to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get sonnes, &amp; daughters, for this immortall world, that neither wil die, nor yet decay: for if there be no new thing vnder the sun, why should we feare the ruine or fall of so faire a fabricke with the steddie earth, his center to beare vp all, and the cope of heauen a couer to shroud all? Come (say they) let vs lay our pleasures as on an heape, let vs lap our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights together, let vs solace our selues in the sweetnes of our sin, there is no feare of vengeance, there is no fire of violence.</p>
            <p>Of such mockers the world is full, who being filled with diuers lusts, haue made a league with death, and a couenant with hell,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176871:13"/>in putting farre off the euill day,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4.5.</note> not knowing that the patience, long suffering, and bountifulnes of God, leadeth to repentance.</p>
            <p>But thou (ô mocker) after thine hardnes, and heart that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not repent, heapest vnto thy selfe wrath against the day of wrath, and of the iust iudgment of God, who will reward euery man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his works.</p>
            <p>But leaue we these fleshly Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures to the iudgement of that great day, &amp; come we to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent matter in hand, and proofe that it shall be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Enoch,</hi> the seuenth from <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude.</hi> 14.15.</note> prophecied of it, saying, Behold the Lord commeth with thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of his Saints to giue iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment against all men, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke all the vngodly of all their wicked deeds. Where first we see
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176871:14"/>how the babe was buried in it birth: I meane the world was no sooner made by God, and mard by man, but euen in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning there went from <hi>Enoch</hi> a pregnant prophecie of it ending, yea and before the first floud was out, the last fire was in, to assure the wicked of both worlds, that their sinnes should neuer go vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punished. Againe, <hi>Enochs</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie, was of such certaintie, that he prophecied it done, ere it was begun: And in vew ere it was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly seene, and not by a probable coniecture, but by a liuely and true demonstration, thus, <hi>Ecce: Behold the Lord cōmeth, &amp;c.</hi> Last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as you may there see, he iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth all persons without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any, all sinnes without missing of one, sinnes of the soule, sinnes of the body, sinnes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176871:14"/>of omission, sinnes of cōmission, and all this in the assembly of all his Saints, for his greater glorie, their good, and for the wofull confusion of the wicked.</p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>Daniel</hi> saith;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9.10.</note> I beheld till the thrones were set, and the fierie streames issued out, till the iudgment was prepared, and the bookes were opened, with thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand thousands ministring vnto him, and ten thousand thousands standing before him. Where I pray you obserue with me what <hi>Daniel</hi> sawe in vision by the bancks of <hi>Hulay,</hi> many misteries cōcerning the <hi>Messias</hi> &amp; Sauiour of all the world, his great humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation in his birth, death, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, with his exaltation to glorie in his resurrection, ascention, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation, second comming, and finall iudgement.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:176871:15"/>
            <p>Of which iudgement, this Scripture was sufficient warning and warrantie to all the world, that the proces were out to som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon it, &amp; that with expedition: for 1. the thrones were prepared to shew his readines 2. the anciēt of daies was set, to shew his reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. 3. Garments white as snowe, to shew his integritie. 4. And eyes like flaming fire, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his seueritie: 5. wheeles bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, to tell vs he is a comming: 6. And streames of fire issuing, to teach vs, that he wil haue no stop. What should I say more? 7 Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riads of men and Angels atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to declare his maiestie. 8. And with bookes opened, to make good his promises laid downe in his word, which word as the Apostle saith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 12.48.</note> shall iudge all in the last day.</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:176871:15"/>
            <p>treadings of all the godly kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping their pathes, hath so tract the way, and beaten the doctrine, as it were a death to our bodies, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to our soules, nay damnation to both, either to put off the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that great day, or to make doubt thereof.</p>
            <p>If scriptures cannot perswade you that there shall be a iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the end of mans creation may: who vndoubtedly was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated of God, to this end that he should be the Image, the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting temple, where he would be worshipped, dwelll, communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate himselfe, and would impart his blessings, now although the end for which man was created, (which is perfect blessednes) is hindered diuers waies: yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily at some time it wil come, and God will obtaine it, for it is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:176871:16"/>not likely, or probable, that man was made for these miseries: but it is also certaine, that the most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent of all creatures was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a better end, and therefore must there needs be at length a change from toyle to rest, from miserie to mercie, and from this wretched life, to a better being.</p>
            <p>In hope whereof, the Saints of God haue bene raised vp from time to time, in the daies of their affliction, they haue swallowed voall difficulties, and vndergone all dangers, to attaine the end of their blessednes, whereunto they were ordained. So <hi>Iob</hi> did when he said, <hi>I know that my redeemer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> shall see him with these eyes.</hi> So <hi>Dauid</hi> did, when he said, <hi>I should verily haue fainted, but that I trust to see the goodnes of God in the lād of the liuing.</hi> So <hi>Paul</hi> did,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:176871:16"/>when he said, I suppose that the afflictions of this life, are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the glorie that shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed.</p>
            <p>And by this argument of the Lords abiding in vs, and we in him, in a better life, is confirmed the happines of our bodies: as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations for the Lord to dwell in, according to that.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19.</note>
               <hi>Knowe yee not that your body is the temple of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost which is in you? &amp;c.</hi> O hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie Christians, if you knew your owne happines, either what you are, or what you haue, you are the temples of God: such you are, and ye haue the holy Ghost with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you, so ye haue. Much adoe there is in this world, where the habitation of God is, where he dwelleth, and where he will be worshipped. One runneth to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem:</hi> another to <hi>Samaria:</hi> one
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:176871:17"/>to <hi>Rome,</hi> and another to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <hi>Sepulcher:</hi> some to the shrine of this Saint, and some to that: as to the Ladie at <hi>Loretta,</hi> or to <hi>Iames</hi> at <hi>Compostella:</hi> some say hee is the God of the Mountaine, some of the <hi>Valley:</hi> some say hee is in the <hi>Pax,</hi> some in the <hi>Oste,</hi> some in the holy graine, &amp; medal: but we say no, and for a check to all, that the habitation of God is with men, and that Christ doth dwell in our harts by faith; Open, ô o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen therefore, your euerlasting doores, that this King of glorie may come in.</p>
            <p>Newe <hi>Ierusalem</hi> came downe from God out of heauen, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a Bride, trimmed for her Husband, with twelue gates of pearles, and the streete of pure golde, yet I sawe no Temple, (saith <hi>Iohn</hi>) therein: to teach vs,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:176871:17"/>that when fire hath fined vs, fitte for our GOD, wee shall dwell in him, and hee in vs. For as now (in the Kingdome of grace) hee that sanctifieth, and they that are sanctified, are both one: So then, in the Kingdome of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, hee that glorifieth, and they that are glorified, shall bee both one.</p>
            <p>Lastlie, if neither Scripture, not the ende of mans Creation to blessednes, can perswade you, yet let the Iustice of God moue you, that there shall bee a iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; For shall not the God of all the world doe according to right, and that is, that it may goe well with the good, and euill with the wicked and refractory: but this commeth not to passe in this life, nay rather, it goeth well with the wicked in this world,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:176871:18"/>and euill with the good and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and therfore there must needs remaine another life wherein the iudge of all the world shall do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to right: for so saith the blessed Apostle,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.6.7.</note>
               <hi>It is a righteous thing with God, to recompence tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to them that trouble you, and to you which are troubled, rest with vs when the Lord Iesus shall shewe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe from heauen with his mightie Angels.</hi> Whereunto also accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned glutton,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.25.</note>
               <hi>Remember that thou in thy life time receiuedst thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, and Lazarus paine, now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is he comforted, and thou art tormented.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this life, to shewe that he is mercifull, the Lord beareth with all, and ballanceth none: but in another, to shew that he is iust, he will ballance all, &amp; beare with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:176871:18"/>none, for euery one shall receiue according to that he hath done in this life, be it good or euil: here the sunne shineth vpon the iust &amp; vniust, here the raigne falleth vpon the field of the foole, aswell as vpon the closures of the wise: here beautie, strength, honour, and skill, are indifferētly bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as vpon the elect of God, so vpon the reprobate from God: here be the outward things of this life, it is not possible to know who is in the fauour of God, and who is not. But when the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is out, and these daies are done, then downe goe the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and the godly shall be exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: horror, hell and death, shall be the doome of the damned: heauen, ioy, and life, shall be the lot of the righteous: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when you see here on earth,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:176871:19"/>things so vneuenly dealt: Know the day will come, when the dole shall be more equallie diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; in the meane time, of the prosperity of the wicked, and of their suddaine destruction, read <hi>Iob. 21.7. &amp;c. Psalme 37.1.</hi> and <hi>Psal.</hi> 10.1.73.3. <hi>Ieremie</hi> 12.1.2.3. <hi>Esdras</hi> 3.33.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Hauing thus proued vnto you from holy scripture, 2. From the ende of mans Creation, 3. And from the Iustice of God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, that Iudgement shall come, as it is in my Text; It now remaines, we come to the second part and question moued; to wit, Who shall bee our Iudge at that dreadfull day?</p>
            <p n="2">2 Wherevnto I answere, that all Iudgement shall be divolued into the handes of Christ,
<note place="margin">Who shalbe our Iudge?</note> and he shall be our Iudge then, who is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:176871:19"/>our aduocate now, <hi>Inde venturus</hi> is an Article of your Creede, yee may belieue it, thence shall hee come to iudge both the quicke and the dead:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.31.</note> The Lord hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a day (saith the Apostle) in the which hee will iudge the world in Righteousnes, by that man whom hee hath appointed: whereof hee hath giuen an assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to all men, in that hee hath raised him from the dead.</p>
            <p>And againe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.35.</note> the Father loueth the Sonne (saith Christ) and hath giuen all things into his handes. And againe, all things are giuen vnto mee of my Father.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.27.</note> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, he hath cōmitted all iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto the Sonne. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.30.</note> then shal appeare the signe of the Son of man in heauen, and all the Tribes of the earth shall mourne, and shall see the Sonne
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:176871:20"/>of man comming in the clouds of heauen.</p>
            <p>I alsty,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10.</note> we shall all appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the iudgemēt feat of Christ, that euery man may receiue the things, which are done in this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, according to that he hath done, whether it be good or euil: whence I gather, that all power in heauen, in earth, and hell, is giuen to the man Christ, in heauen to open it, in earth, to redeeme it; in hell, to shut it; the Cherubins giue place and passage to our Christ, &amp; to the children whom God hath giuen him, the wide mouth &amp; gulfe of hel is shut from his Saints, by him, and there he keepeth in both diuels and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: in the might of his power, he hath power ouer the diseased to cure them, ouer sinners to saue them, ouer death and doome, to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:176871:20"/>dissolue them, he checketh sinne with righteousnes, &amp; cancelleth the rigor of the lawe with the mildnes of the Gospell, all power is giuen vnto him to conuert men to the faith, to confirme Angels in the faith, &amp; to confine all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences to such obedience as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth.</p>
            <p>As, &amp; if he should say, all rule, all right, all reward, all venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is mine: all power ouer men, I can conuert thē: all power ouer diuels, I can controule them: all power ouer the dead, I can raise them: all power ouer the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I can iudge them, &amp; giue to euery man as his worke shall be.</p>
            <p>Or, as and if he should yet say more powerfully, It is giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, <hi>Ad creandum, adrecrean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, ad glorificandum,</hi> In the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:176871:21"/>I was with the father, I was his mouth, I said, and it was done. In the redemption, I was my selfe alone, I bled and ye were deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: and for the Diademe of your glorie, it is put into my hand, and I haue power to set it where I wil: It is giuen vnto me, a man as you are in all things (sinne onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) and at whom all men are offended, and I vniustlie cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured: but I shall come againe, with my Fan in my hand, &amp; win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now all with vpright iudgement. O wonderfull misterie of the match of Gods Maiestie with our miserie. <hi>Carnem nostram regnare in coelo super omnia:</hi> that our flesh should iudge all on earth, and raigne aboue all in heauen.</p>
            <p>And here you Popes wane your plenarie power of indulgence, you are intruders vpon the Lords
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:176871:21"/>possession, his power is <hi>plena, iusta, firma,</hi> full without limitation: for so it is said, all power is giuen, &amp;c. It is iust without intrusion, it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, not stollen: it is firme &amp; sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, without change: it is giuen of the father, according to that all power is giuen vnto me of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Ruat Orbis, &amp; Orcus, Illa erit secura.</hi> But I say againe, you are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intruders vpon the Lords posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, such power was neuer giuen you, &amp; therefore your kingdome cannot stand, but fall to hell from whence it came: To tread vpon the necks of Kings and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours it is your pride, to pine poore soules in a fained fire, it is your folly: &amp; either to push soules into hell, or to fetch any thence (as you say you did the soule of <hi>Traian</hi>) it is your grosse impietie. <hi>Fiat iustitia, &amp; pereat mundus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:176871:22"/>
            <p>Let the right of Christ take place, and the world of your wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes vanish.</p>
            <p>Pardon me, to expostulate the right of my Christ with the wrōg you haue done him, &amp; tell whats the reason you are so rebellious against the Lord, his crowne and dignitie, is it for that his pouertie, matcheth not with your pride? or is it, for that his wretched crowne of thornes, wayeth not with the Diademe of your gold set with Saphires? is it for that our poore king tryumphed vpon an asse, and you ride vpon your steeds of state, trapped with Diamonds &amp; champing vpon gold? Is it for that Christ conquered in his pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and you glorie in your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, euery battaile of the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour is with noise, and tumbling of garmēts in blood, such is your
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:176871:22"/>fight, euer in fire, &amp; still in blood. But vnto vs a child is borne, and a sonne is giuen, and the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is vpon his shoulders: sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly surely, I should neuer thinke my self to be of the true Church, but for her lenitie, nor you to be the malignāt Church, but for your crueltie.</p>
            <p>I cannot but wonder to see so high treason committed against the Lord, euen in this particular point of iudgement, by men of this world, of whom I may say, their madnes is knowne vnto all men, the Lord is at hand.</p>
            <p>Madnes (I say) in this, and treasonable furie, that they dare robbe the Lord of his honour, and take to themselues plenarie power of Indulgence, power to purge sinne, power to forgiue sinne, and power to iudge sinne,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:176871:23"/>who durst euer haue presumed to do this: but that man of sinne? who hath aduanced himselfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all that is called God, and doth sit as God in the Temple of God, shewing himselfe that he is God.</p>
            <p>You are religiously wise to know whom I meane, I meane that man of <hi>Rome</hi> is that great Rebel against God, &amp; his Christ, in that he hath taken vpon him in his papall pride, not onely pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie and power ouer men: but iurisdiction ouer all creatures, in heauen, earth, and hell, to binde or loose, saue or spill, in so much, that if he should thrust thousands of soules into hell, (as one of their Canonists hath it) yet no man may say, <hi>Curita facis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now for conclusion of this point, and to leaue these tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:176871:23"/>Iurdens, and to wash a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in <hi>Shilo,</hi> if any soule be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous to search into the causes, why the man Christ shall be iudge ouer all at that day, let him know, that the Church is to be glorified by the same mediator, by whom, and for whom it was iustified, according to that,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 17.31.</note>
               <hi>God wil iudge the world in righteousnes, by the man whom he hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I say appointed a sacrifice, a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, a iudge, a sacrifice on his crosse, a mediator at his right hand in heauen, a Iudge on earth at that dreadfull day, all appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God, all vndertaken by Christ, that he might haue the primacie, prime, and pride (if I may so say) of our full regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in grace, and restauration to glorie.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:176871:24"/>
            <p>Againe, the man Christ must iudge all, that we may haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: knowing him to be our iudge, who is of vs, bone of our bone: and flesh of our flesh: he is our brother, our husband, our head: and therfore saith <hi>Bernard,</hi> the father of mercies, and God of all consolations, will iudge men by men, that in so great a confusion of euils, semblance of natures might yeeld comfort: to the which is annexed, a promise to the faithfull beleeuer, when he saith; He that beleeueth in the Sonne of God, hath euerlasting life, and shall not come into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: but for the vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and such as contumeliouslie haue set themselues against the Lord, they shall looke vpon the man Christ whom they haue pierced.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:176871:24"/>
            <p>But to proceed with the rest, I doubt not but out of that which alreadie hath bin deliuered, you are fully resolued that there shall be a iudgment, as also that Christ shall be our iudge, in that great day. It now remaines, we make knowne vnto you, how he will iudge the world, and by what proces.</p>
            <p>Where first obserue,
<note place="margin">Generall Summons.</note> that he wil go by general summōs of all, all shall appeare before the tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall seate of Christ, all that haue bene, all that are, and all that shall be to the worlds ending, young and old, rich, and poore, Iew, and gentile, bond and free, noble and ignoble, from the king in his throne, to the channell sweeper in the streete, al shal appeare, giue their attendance, and receiue their doome: Hell shal be shaken,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:176871:25"/>and the graues shall open, the Sea shal giue vp her dead, Beasts, Fish, and Fowle, shall render the corps they haue deuoured; Yea, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen it selfe shall be emptied, of Saints and Soules, in that great day.</p>
            <p>I say in that great day, when the Lord shall send his Angells with a great sounde of a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.31.</note> and they shall gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Elect, from the fower windes, and from one end of the heauens to another.</p>
            <p>I say,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuelat.</hi> 1.7.</note> in that great day, when hee shall come in the clouds, and euery eye shall see him, yea euen they which pierced him throgh, and all kindreds of the earth shall waile before him: Euen so A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, saith the blessed Apostle, to make it as sure and certaine to bee, as if it were alreadie done.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:176871:25"/>Whervnto accordeth <hi>Christ,</hi> whē to take away the wonder thereof, he said thus; Maruell not at this, for the houre shall come, in the which, all that are in the graues shall heare his voice. Now if such shalbe the shoute of his summōs, so loude, so shrill, and so piercing, that the liuing shalbe appalled to heare it, and the ghastly graue to beare it, how should wee but groane, and grieue to tell it?</p>
            <p>When hee came in Mercie to redeeme the world, it would not be sommoned, so softe and silent was his voyce, like a shower of raine vpon a fleece of woll, but at his comming in iudgement, his sommons wilbe more sounding, for the Lord himselfe shall des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend from heauen, with a shoute, and with the voice of th'ark-An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, and wth the Trumpet of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:176871:26"/>God. As, and if he should say, to heighthen the call, If the shout of the Lord reach thee not, the Arkangels voyce shall: and if nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the shout of the one, nor the voyce of the other, will rouse thee, the trumpet of God shall raise thee vp.</p>
            <p>Seuen rammes hornes weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sounded from the weake mouth of man, ruinated the high walles of <hi>Ierico:</hi> How much more then shall the loud trumpet of God, blowne from his fierie mouth, shake and sommon, both the liuing and the dead? Surely, surely, as his last comming shal be suddē, like lightning flashing out of the East, and seene in the west, and all in the twinckling of an eye, so shall the sommons be, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, earth, and hell, shall heare it all at once: and no sooner shall
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:176871:26"/>they see their iudge, but they shal be sommoned to iudgement: of which dreadfull day, &amp; peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie sommons, so oftē as I think (saith a good Father) <hi>Toto cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore contremisco;</hi> I tremble in my thoughts, and shake in all my ioints; for whether I eate, on whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I drinke, whether I sleepe, or whether I wake, or whatsoeuer thing I do, me thinks I still heare that terrible trumpet sounding in mine eares, <hi>Arise ye dead, and come to iudgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus hauing sommoned all to make their appearance, next,
<note place="margin">The exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> he will proceed to examine their cause, euery man according to that he hath done in this life, be it good or euill: for it stands with all right, lawe, &amp; equitie, that no man should be condemned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he come to his triall, the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:176871:27"/>Lord would not proceede with <hi>Adam</hi> till hee had examined his cause, and saide, <hi>Adam</hi> where art thou? what hast thou done? who told thee that thou wast na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked? hast thou eaten of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Tree? Nor would hee proceede against <hi>Caine,</hi> till hee had called him to an account, and saide, where is thy brother <hi>Abel?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioshua</hi> examined <hi>Achan</hi> of the Babilonish garment, and wedge of gold, ere he proceeded to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iudgement. And the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners that knewe not God, after the Prophet was taken by <hi>Lot,</hi> and adiudged to be cast into the Sea, yet did not proceede to execution, till they had exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him vpon these interrogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Tell vs what euill hast thou done? what is thine Occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:176871:27"/>and whence commest thou? which is thy Countrey? and of what people art thou?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Israel</hi> may not enter <hi>Canaan,</hi> till they haue sent forth <hi>Explora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores terrae,</hi> Searchers of the land, and before the destruction of the Cittie, the Lord will search <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem</hi> with Lights,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.12.</note> and will visite the men that are frozen in their dregges.</p>
            <p>And now (good Lord) <hi>Quid in Babilone tutum, si in Ierusalem manet scrutinium?</hi> How shall <hi>Babylon</hi> bee safe, if <hi>Ierusalem</hi> must be fyned; and if a virgin daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Syon</hi> may not passe without a search? how can <hi>Babylon</hi> escape without triall? This world is chaffe, it must be winnowed, in the great day of the Lords scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinie, betwixt the sommons and the sentence, there must be an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:176871:28"/>that when the Lord hath made inquisition for blood,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psalme</hi> 9.12.</note> hee may remember it, and not forget the complainte of the poore.</p>
            <p>Now if any man doubt wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he shall be examined in that great day, let him be sure that the Lord will examine all our thoughs, all our words, all our deeds, and all the time we haue spent in this world, all our thoughts according to that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisition shall be made, <hi>for the thoughtes of the vngodlie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wisedome.</hi> 1.9.</note>
               <hi>and the sound of his words shall come vnto God for the correction of his iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> Whereunto <hi>Oregen</hi> agreeth. Our very thoughts shall either acquit or cōdemne our soules, in that fearefull day, and not the thoughts that then shall be, but the thoughts that are euen now
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:176871:28"/>in vs, whose impressions left in our hearts, are as letters in paper, which when all secrets shall be disclosed, will be easily read.</p>
            <p>Next vnto our thoughts, the Lord will examine our wordes, yea all our words, <hi>Non tam mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiosa, quam otiosa,</hi> aswel such as are spoken in our myrth, as in our malice, for of euery idle word saith Christ, that men shal speake, they shall giue an account there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of at the day of iudgement.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 12.36.</note> And surely all are idle that are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and tend either to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God, or good of his Church;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hierom: super Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit.</hi> 12.</note>
               <hi>Quicquid non adificat au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diētes in periculum vertitur eloquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> whatsoeuer doth not edifie the hearer, turnes to the danger of the speaker.</p>
            <p>Now may you say, your tongues are your owne, for they
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:176871:29"/>are bought with a price, and if you will be quit of your recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the great accoūt, let your words be few and faithfull, euer poudered with grace, that you may finde grace in time of need.</p>
            <p>When the Lord hath done with our thoughts and words, then will he come to our deeds for God will bring euery worke into iudgement.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccles.</hi> 12.44.</note> With euery se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret thing, whether it be good or euill. All our workes shall then be discouered, examined, &amp; try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by the touch of fire, which if they can abide, then shall they be fined for heauen: if not, they must be fuell for hell.</p>
            <p>Lastly, all our time must come to tryall, and the Lord will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine how we haue bestowed euery yeare, euery moneth, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day and minute thereof, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:176871:29"/>when time shal be no more, they that haue redeemed it in the kingdome of grace, shall haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie in glorie. But all such as haue neglected time, and haue not knowne the day of their visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, nor the things that belong to their peace, they shall haue shame, and confusion for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more:
<note place="margin">Bernar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</note>
               <hi>Omne tempus nobis impen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum: requiritur a nobis qualiter sit expensum,</hi> All the time the Lord hath bestowed vpon vs, he will require how it hath bene bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for him.
<note place="margin">Witnesses produced.</note> To this fierie triall and due examination, sufficient testies, and witnesses shall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, to conuict the sinner, though himselfe would be silent and answere nothing, in that dreadfull day all creatures shall accuse them of guilt,
<note place="margin">The crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> and presse the punishment. Now they that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:176871:30"/>grone with vs after a deliuerāce, shall grieue for vs, and witnes to our woe, that we haue bene wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, <hi>In illo die</hi> (saith <hi>Chrysostome) nihilest quod respondeamus vbi coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lū, &amp; terra, Sol, &amp; luna, dies, &amp; noc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; totus mundus stabunt aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus nos, in testimoniū peccatorū nos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trorum.</hi> In that day we shall haue nothing to answere, when hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and earth, sunne, &amp; moone, daies and nights, &amp; all the world shall stand against vs as witnesses of our sinnes.</p>
            <p>If the creatures should say no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<note place="margin">Our sinnes.</note> yet our proper sinnes shall then accuse vs, for all our offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that now lurke in vs, shall then creepe forth and speake to our shame &amp; endles confusion. The Idoll we haue adored shall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse vs of Idolatrie, the mothes of our gaie garments, shall then
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:176871:30"/>accuse vs of intollerable pride, the rust of our gold and siluer, here cankering, our soules shall then accuse vs of auarice, and the stone in the walles shall cry to the timber, oppression: all these shall say we were thy creatures which thou diddest abuse, &amp; now thou shalt be iudged for vs.</p>
            <p>The diuell that old aduersarie,
<note place="margin">The diuell.</note> and accuser of our brethren, shall come in the rancke and say, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quissime iudex iudica hinc esse me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ob culpam qui tuus esse nolint per gratiam, tuus est per naturam, meus per miseram, tuus ob passionem, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ob suationem,</hi> O righteous iudge, doome him to be mine for sinne, who would not be thine by grace: thine in mercy, mine in miserie: thine by thy passion, mine by perswasion: yea Sathan shall then shift to euery circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:176871:31"/>and corner of our sinnes, saying; In such a time, at such a place, with such a person, and in such sort hast thou sinned: It was done in the sight of thy God and his sonne, therefore crie sonne, cry sinne, cry conscience with me, shall not the iudge of all the world doe according to right?</p>
            <p>Lastly,
<note place="margin">Our consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> and not the least of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, the conscience shall step forth in that dreadfull day, a iudge of our soules, either accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing or excusing all our actions: with a Iurie of witnesses, euerrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to giue vp the verdit; I say a iudge of it selfe, for who knowes the things that are in a man, but the spirit which is in man? where doubtles the spirit is taken for the iudge of the conscience: nor only that, but God himselfe shall be it iudge. In which sense the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:176871:31"/>Apostle saith, <hi>God is greater then our hearts.</hi> And <hi>Iob,</hi> my witnes is in heauen: Nay more, the consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will haue Sathan a iudge, suggesting the sinne, and vrging the iudgement, stirring vp suries to affright the soule, as he did in <hi>Nero,</hi> who after he had murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his mother <hi>Agrippina,</hi> neuer tooke pleasant sleepe, but was frighted with feare and furie, till he was dead.</p>
            <p>Lastly, men withall,
<note place="margin">Men with whome we haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersed.</note> will be witnesses to accuse our consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Nam in hac re valde sumus improuidi: quod peccamus raro soli.</hi> Herein are we improuident, that seldome we doe sinne alone. But for the most part, haue associats and fellowes in transgression, to witnes our woe: the thiefe, the Adulterer, the wantō, the Braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, the Idolater: the drinker, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:176871:32"/>drunkard, seldome sinne alone, but haue men their associates to witnes their wickednes: <hi>Ananias</hi> had his wife priuie to his fact: <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> had <hi>Eue,</hi> the Serpēt &amp; God, priuie to his transgression: <hi>Iudas</hi> had the Iewes acquainted with his sinne: the Soldiours whose guide he was to take Christ, the Disciples who sawe his treason, Christ whom he did betray, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than his perswader, and God the gouernour of all things to their appointed ends. Whereupon I may say, that the conscience is a thousand witnesses, it is both iudge and iurie, accuser and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner, neuer forgetting, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing the delinquent.</p>
            <p>It is the readiest remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, and the sharpest censor that can be in the soule of man; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that, <hi>scit conscientia omnia,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:176871:32"/>&amp; adcensuram reuocat, dicta, facta, cogitata,</hi> it knoweth all words, deeds, and thoughts, &amp; yeeldeth no grace, but pronounceth sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence against it selfe rigorously, and speedily.</p>
            <p>One calleth it <hi>Sillogisimus prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus,</hi> a restlesse reasoning euer in contemplation: another calls it vicegerent, from whose face and furie thou canst neuer, flee, shun thou maiest the sight of man, but neuer cansts thou auoyd the eye of God, nor the sighes of thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie hart, it is a worme euer grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it is a fire euer burning, the further thou fliest, the faster it hasteth after, &amp; when thou dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mest thy selfe safest, then art thou in greatest danger: sleeping it frighteth, waking it feareth, <hi>Alas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor est,</hi> it is a furie, tied to a life euer dying, and to a death euer liuing:
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:176871:33"/>To cōclude, it is horrible as hell, endles, easeles, and remediles for paine and passion.</p>
            <p>Now if such be the conscience that shall accuse vs: then blessed is the good conscience that shall quit vs, in that great day, of which the Apostle speaketh, when he saith;
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12.</note>
               <hi>Our reioycing is the testimonie of our conscience, that in simplicitie and godly purenes, and not in fleshly wisedome, but by the grace of God, we haue had our conuersation in this world, and most of all to you wards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This conscience is the title of honour, the Temple of <hi>Salomon,</hi> the Orchard of delight, the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den bed, it is earths solace, &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens ioy. <hi>Nihil iucundius, nihil tutius, nihil diutius bona cōscientia, fremat or bis &amp; orcus, illa erit secura:</hi> there is nothing more sweet, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more safe: nothing more
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:176871:33"/>durable then a good conscience.</p>
            <p>Rage world, roare hell, it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies at quiet. Children in their play, saith the poet can tell one to another, thou shalt be great if thou be good. <hi>Hic murus Aeneus esto: Nil conscire sibi, nulla pallesce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re culpa.</hi> Let this be thy brazen wall, to knowe no guilt by thy selfe, nor feare no fault to appall thee.</p>
            <p>For the conscience, as another saith more diuinely, <hi>Tenella res est, adeo, vt in magnis, it a in paruis sape grauiter hareat,</hi> It is a tender thing, sticking as much at little sinnes, as at great ones, which made the king to charge <hi>Shemey</hi> with the transgression of all he had committed against <hi>Dauid</hi> his Father, when he saith:
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Kings</hi> 2.44.</note>
               <hi>Thou knowest all the wickednes whereunto thine hart is priuie:</hi> thy great sinnes
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:176871:34"/>and thy little sinnes, all are alike, and now thou shalt bee iudged for both.</p>
            <p>And now for further proces in the Lords busines,
<note place="margin">His sentēce wilbe right, not wicked.</note> at that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day, hauing thus sōmoned all flesh, and brought euery thought to tryall; it remaines we see how hee will come, <hi>Ad sententiandum, &amp; ad seperandum:</hi> to sentence our cause, and seuer our persons.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For his sentence, it will bee right,
<note place="margin">with might.</note> for what might, or power in this world can wrest it? No feare, no loue, no reward, no ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, which oftentimes doe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert Iustice on earth, can staine it in heauen; For if Iustice be a Virgin, and may not be deflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with men, how much more shall the Iudge of all the world proceed without corruption? </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Neuer will he be backed with
<note place="margin">Nor feare.</note>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:176871:34"/>feare, in that hee is more mightie then all: acccording to that of <hi>Eliphaz</hi> the <hi>Temanite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 32.</note> Is it for feare of thee that hee will accuse thee, or goe with thee to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Nay, the Lord is so farre from feare of anie, that the more mightie they are who offend, the more seuere hee is to plague,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wisedome.</hi> 6.8.</note>
               <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, potenter, tormenta patientur;</hi> the mightie abide the sorer triall, and hee that is Lord ouer all, will spare no person: neither shall he feare anie greatnes, for hee hath made the small and great, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for all alike; wherevnto ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordeth that of <hi>Esay, Topheth</hi> is prepared of old,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esay.</hi> 30.33.</note> it is euen prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the King, he hath made it deepe and large, the burning thereof, is fire and much wood, and the breath of the Lord, like a riuer of brimstone doth kindle it.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:176871:35"/>
            <p n="3">3 Nor will he be moued with the loue or affection of any,
<note place="margin">Nor loue.</note> who is most iust: no people, no kindred, no parētage, no kindnes, no cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesie, may pleade priuiledge with the Lord, not <hi>Iudah</hi> his harts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, not <hi>Israel</hi> the plāt of his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure; If <hi>Ieconiah</hi> were as the signet of my right hand,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 5.1.</note> yet would I cast him off, &amp; though <hi>Moses</hi> &amp; <hi>Samuel</hi> stood before me (saith the Lord) yet mine affection could not be towards this wicked people:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezec.</hi> 14.14.</note> yea if these three men, <hi>Noah, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Iob,</hi> were amongst thē, they should deliuer but their owne soules by their righteousnes, saith the Lord: the iust iudge of all the world, will doe according to right, and euery one shalbe iudged according to that he hath done with vpright iudgement.
<note place="margin">Nor luker.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 Againe, this iudge shall be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:176871:35"/>corrupted with no gifts, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wa ds of any: for that he is <hi>ditissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> the richest of all,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 6.35</note> what nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth he the wealth of anie? The wise king saith, he cānot beare the sight of any ransome, neither will he consent, thogh thou augment thy gifts: <hi>Veniet, illa dies veniet, in qua valebunt plus pura corda, quam astuta verba, &amp; conscientia bona, quam marsupia plena,</hi> that day will come, in which, pure hearts will more preuaile, thē guilt tōgues, &amp; a good consciēce, thē a full purse.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Lastly, he will be tainted with no malice, or hatred to anie,
<note place="margin">with no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred.</note>
               <hi>quia optimus, in eo enim qui optimus est, odium cadere non potest, quod pessi mum est.</hi> Hatred, which is the worst of all,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wisedome.</hi> 10.</note> can neuer be found in him, who is best of all: thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uest all things that are, and hatest nothing that thou hast made: hee
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:176871:36"/>that loueth all in his <hi>Mercie,</hi> would punish none, but for his Iudgement: and therefore one saith well, <hi>Egreditur Deus de loco suo dum punit:</hi> the Lord is not at home, whilest hee punisheth, which made him to grieue, when he thought vpon the affliction of <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Israel;</hi> How shall I giue thee vp <hi>Ephraim?</hi> How shall I deliuer thee <hi>Israel?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hose.</hi> 11.8.</note> How shall I make thee as <hi>Adniah?</hi> How shall I set thee as <hi>Zeboim?</hi> mine heart is turned within me, my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentings are rolled together, and therefore it is worthy due ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation, to see that euen then, when the firie floud of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is out, how hee cooleth it with the sweet springs of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, not iudging the wicked in that great day, for sinnes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, but for sinnes of omis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:176871:36"/>not for that they haue done, but for that which they haue not done: nor for the breach of the first table against God, but for the breach of the secōd table against men: according to that, <hi>I was an hungred, and you gaue me no meate: I thursted, and you gaue me no drinke, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I adde,
<note place="margin">His sentence shall be irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocable.</note> as his sentence shall be right, so shall it be irreuocable, like the lawes of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Persians,</hi> neuer reuersed vpon any intreatie, <hi>Ite &amp; venite,</hi> shall deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all, the one by the lawe, the other by the Gospell: and <hi>Non noui vos</hi> shall shut the doore, the blessed within, and the damned without: I say the sweet sentence of saluation, <hi>Come yee,</hi> shall fall vpon the blessed, according to the Gospell, the lawe yeelding thereunto, through the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:176871:37"/>of faith, but vpon the damned shall fall, <hi>Go yee:</hi> the Gospell yeelding thereunto, for their vnbelief. Besides, <hi>I know you not,</hi> will be a wofull sentence, and the heauiest doome, that euer was determined. For what am I the better that I haue bene knowne in this world, by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of my place, or greatnes of my person, if kings haue knowne me, nobilitie and gentrie haue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured me, if wife, children, and familie, haue fawned vpon me, what am I the better? If I haue bene knowne by the beautie of my face and comely stature, by the strēgth of my arme, or excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of my wit, what am I the better for all these? If Christ will not knowe me, at that dreadfull day? If in sicknes when all plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures shall be forsaken, if in death,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:176871:37"/>when all delights shall be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, if in doome, when all this world shall leaue me, and I haue none to leane vnto but my Christ, and if then he will not knowe me, what shall become of me? If they that would cannot, and if he that can will not, what shall I say, but <hi>O yee hilles couer me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely, surely,
<note place="margin">His wrath implacable.</note> as his sentence wilbe irreuocable, his wrath will be implacable, and he will yeeld to no intreatie: for be it the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned shall say, Lord we are not worthy to possesse thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, yet let it please thee we may sit at thy seate: but he shall answere, <hi>Discedite a me,</hi> not so, but depart from me: betwixt you and me there shall be a great gulfe, gastly to the sight, and impassible for any presence.</p>
            <p>Againe, be it they shall say, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:176871:38"/>thou expell vs from thee, yet dismisse vs with a blessing: but he shall answere no: <hi>Ite maledicti,</hi> goe yee with a curse. Be it they say vnto him, Lord, if we must a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and with a malediction, yet send vs into some place of rest and refreshing: but he shall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere againe no; <hi>Ite in ignem,</hi> goe yee into the fire for fuell of hell. Be it yet they plead further, and say, Lord if we must to the fire, let it haue an end, and be but for a season, but he shall answere no: yee must in <hi>Ignem aeternum,</hi> into euerlasting fire, where is weeping and wayling, and gnashing of teeth.</p>
            <p>Lastly. Be it they yet say, Good God if it must needs be so, let vs be ruled with some pittifull prince, and haue some societie that good is: but he shal answere;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:176871:38"/>euen with the diuell, and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, <hi>Pro domino habebitis diabolum maiorem, pro socijs vero doemones minores,</hi> Ye shall haue the prince of diuels for your king, and lesser diuels for your companions:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 9.6.</note> ye shall seeke death &amp; shall not finde it, and shall desire to die, &amp; death shall flie from you.</p>
            <p>Thus hauing sentenced all,
<note place="margin">Vpon his sentence, the Lord will sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</note> there must be a separation, <hi>Goates</hi> to hell, <hi>sheepe</hi> to heauē, the good to God, euer to be blessed, the euill to Sathan, euer to be accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed: for without shall be dogges, lyers, and libertines, but within shall be the faire flocke, and holy assembly: vpon the sentence, the sinners shall shrinke downward, and in feare of their fall, cry to the mountaines couer vs, but the godly shall haue boldnes, and be aduanced to sit with their Christ,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:176871:39"/>as assistance, knowe yee not saith the Apostle, that the Saints shall iudge the world.</p>
            <p>Death is a diuider, and so is doome, <hi>two shall be in the field, the one shall be taken, and the other shall be refused: two shall be on the house top, the one shall be taken, the other shall be refused, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What sinne hath gathered, righteousnes shall scatter, and the Lord like the gathering Host, <hi>Dan,</hi> shall come last of all and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the good corne into his barne, but burne the chaffe with vnquencheable fire, for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked shall not stand in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor sinners in the assembly of the righteous.</p>
            <p>And that the seuering may be as sure to stand, as the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence without change, the iudge himselfe, and none but he, will
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:176871:39"/>pronounce the one, and defie the other: Angels may gather as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly we haue said, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Officium iudices est &amp; ad solum christum pertinet,</hi> Angels I say by the Lords appointment, may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the elect, from the foure cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the world, in that generall sommons, but to sentēce all, is in the iust mouth of the <hi>Lord,</hi> &amp; to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate all, is in his powerfull hād: and now, that in this world he suffereth a mixture of both, it is his great mercy, therby to moue vs to vnfained repentance, that hauing so long endured corne and cockle to growe together, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen till the day of his great har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uest, they might then groane vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a iust iudgement, who haue neglected so vedeserued mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. And so to the rest.</p>
            <p>Next in place, are to be consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:176871:40"/>the signes precedent,
<note place="margin">Signes of his care approach.</note> or concurring with that great day, as harbingers of his wrath, and neare approach of his comming. It would be tedious to heare, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing your eares sanctified, with a better truth, as also troubles me for me to speake, being (as I trust) touched with an hotter coale of the Altar, to tell of the idle dreames, and munkish foppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries which superstition hath deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed thereof, in the darke &amp; derne cels of their grosse ignorance.</p>
            <p>Exceeding the signes of the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> ouer and aboue all that are mencioned in the booke of God, or haue fallen from the mouth of Christ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bonauenture</hi> all at a venter, hath marshalled thē to fifteene. Ium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping with <hi>Methodius, Albimazer, Haly,</hi> and others of that rancke;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:176871:40"/>and yet haue left out some which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and the moderne pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists of these our daies haue fondly vrged, as of the comming of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> three yeares and an halfe before the iudgement day. In which times say they, hee should fight with the three Kings of <hi>Libia, Aegipt,</hi> and <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> persecute Christians, and put to death, <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might tell you further, how they tell vs tales what shal fall out for fifteene dayes, next &amp; imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately before the iudgment day: As the 1 day,
<note place="margin">Bonauent. Dieta. 9. <hi>Cap.</hi> 48. De general: iudicio.</note> that the sea shall swell: 15 cubits aboue the highest hilles, and stand in his owne cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter like a wall of brasse. And in the 2. day, shall fall againe to so great an Ebbe, as scarce it shall be seene: in the 3. day, fishes and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritine beasts shall appeare, and so
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:176871:41"/>bellow, as their lowing shal reach the heauens: the 4 day, heauen and earth shall burne with fire: in the 5 day, hearbes and trees shall droppe blood: the 6 day, all buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings shall be ruinated: the 7 day, Rocks shal ruine and breake into eight peeces, &amp; beate one against another, yet so as none shall heare the sound but onely God. The 8 day, shal be so general an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, as neither men nor liuing creature shall be able to stand but fall to the ground: in the 9 day, all the earth shall be euened, moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and hills shal turne to dust: in the 10 day, men shall creepe out of the dennes of the earth, wander like mad men, and neuer speake one to another: in the 11 day, all the bones of the dead shal rise, and stand vpon their sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and all graues shall be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:176871:41"/>that the dead may come forth: in the 12 day, Starres shall fall from heauen, all liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures shall come into the fields lowing, and shall touch neither grasse nor water: in the 13 day, men that are aliue shall die, and shall then arise with those that were dead: in the 14 day, heauen and earth shall burne with the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficies both of earth and aire: in the 15 day, there shall be a new heauen, and a new earth, and the dead shall rise, <hi>secundum virtutes, merita, &amp; demerita, recepturi.</hi> Thus am I bold to touch this their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding grossenes, <hi>vt euitetur,</hi> as an euill to be shunned and laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at, so farre from the light of truth, as is the rest of their popish doctrine, the Lord in his good time open their eyes that they may see with <hi>Hager,</hi> the well of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:176871:42"/>liuing water, and be refreshed with the springs of his word and truth, which yet they haue either rammed vp in their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, or beaten backe, with the Iorden of their ignorance.</p>
            <p>But the signes of Christ his comming shewed in the word, are sanctified with a better spirit, they implie no contradiction, they sauour of no heathenish or fabulous deuise, they checke no scripture, they grieue no good conscience, they prouoke vs ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to good deeds and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, then to any such wilde workes of wonder.</p>
            <p>Christ sitting vpon the mount of <hi>Oliues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.3.</note> his disciples came vnto him apart, saying, <hi>Tell vs when these things shall be?</hi> and what signes shall bee of thy comming, and of the end of the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:176871:42"/>world? <hi>Dominus in monte, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum in alto,</hi> from the height of the hill, hee tells them the depth of his counsell, and yet mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not one of all the former follies, as signes of his comming. Hee tells them of three euills that shall rule, and be rigorous in the latter dayes, &amp; end of the world: 1. Of <hi>Heresie,</hi> which shall spoile the Faith of the Church: 2. Of <hi>Tyrannie,</hi> which shall persecute the members of the Church: 3. And of <hi>Domesticall Enemies,</hi> who shall corrupt the manners of the Church: of all which, wee may iustlie complaine, and crie with the Prophet,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lament.</hi> 1.10.</note>
               <hi>Manum suam misit hostis, ad omnia desiderabilia eius:</hi> The enemie hath stretched out his hand vppon all our pleasant things.</p>
            <p>And surely, if there were no
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:176871:43"/>ther, these were sufficient signes to warne vs euen now, of his nere approch to iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antichrist</hi> in the East, and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist</hi> in the West, haue banded themselues against the Lord, and against his Saintes, practising by all possible and potent meanes, to destroy the Faith of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, and as <hi>Pilate</hi> dealt with the <hi>Galileans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.1.</note> to mingle the blood of his Saintes, with their owne sacrifices.</p>
            <p>If any man say this Prophecie of Christ cannot be meant of the Pope, pardon me, whilst I proue in a word, by the words of Christ there laide downe, that it can be meant of none other, vnlesse you please to drawe in <hi>Mahomets im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posture,</hi> to make full the sinnes of the <hi>Amorites:</hi> the wordes of Christ are these; <hi>Take heede that no
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:176871:43"/>man deceiue you, for many shall come in my name, saying, I am Christ, and shall deceiue many:</hi> whereout I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that they are men, who shall deceiue: Beware of men, so saith Christ elsewhere, as the most fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar euill, to worke euill with those that are euill: 2 Christ saith they are many, so is that <hi>Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> which makes them so to bragge of their multitude, with their king of <hi>Locusts,</hi> and filthy froggs crawling out of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomles pit, and so great a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as well-neere they haue blasted the greene grasse, and growth of the Church in all Christendome, I meane all the orders of <hi>Cardinals, Fryers, Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, Anchorists Iesuits, Seminaries, Nunnes, and Nouices,</hi> all subiect to the pope, that king of <hi>Locusts;</hi> whose name in <hi>Hebrew</hi> is <hi>Abad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:176871:44"/>and in <hi>Greeke Apollion,</hi> 3. saith Christ, they shall come in my name: therby shewing their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of holines, but haue denied the power thereof: 4. they shall come saith Christ, vsurping that they were neuersēt about, but fit as intruders vpon the Lords pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session, without mission, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission: 5. saith Christ, they shall say, I am Christ, vttering their great blasphe my agaīst the Lord: <hi>Popes</hi> haue so said of themselues, <hi>Popes</hi> haue endured to heare it of others, none but Popes euer rose to that height of pride, as to say, Christ and I make one consistorie, and I can doe all that he can: <hi>Claue non errante:</hi> 6. and lastly, their successe shall be mightie, for as Christ saith, they shall deceiue manie, as an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible note of popish impietie,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 3.13.</note>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:176871:44"/>to deceiue, and be deceiued.</p>
            <p>Besides their heresy they haue euer bin branded with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test crueltie, and of all persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that euer were in the Church of God, that of popery hath bene most bloudy in her designs, yet is, and euer (I feare) will bee. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes their sanguinarie Inquisition of <hi>Spaine,</hi> intended against the <hi>Moores,</hi> but inflicted vpon the faithful Christians, whose blood, with his substance, is thereby suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out. Witnes their late Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacre in <hi>France,</hi> when the streetes of <hi>Paris</hi> streamed with the blood of poore protestants. Witnes the dayes of Queene <hi>Marie,</hi> times of triall, when fire and fagots were welnere quenched &amp; spent with the blood of the Innocent. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the ransacking of the bones and graues of the dead, buryed
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:176871:45"/>first, and burned after. Witnesse their late pouder plot against our state, and of greater consequence for killing cruelty, then euer man could haue deuised: if hell had not holpen out, these persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are preābles of the latter day, harbingers of wrath to come, and sure signes of future iudgement, as if the Lord had plainelie said, <hi>Popish curelty</hi> shall forerun my fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry comming.</p>
            <p>As for the last of euills, when I tolde you from Christ, that iniquitie should abound, and the manners of the Church should be corrupted, towards the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment day, that's nothing but the invndation of sinne, wherein the religion shall blend in transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion against the Lord, with A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theists, Nullifideans, Miscreants of the world, and damned crew,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:176871:45"/>to iustifie that of Christ, <hi>Iniquitie shall abound, loue and charitie shall waxe cold:</hi> what said I, shall we of the religion, sort with sinners in their sinne? <hi>O telit not in Gath, &amp;c.</hi> Surely it breaks my hart to think how we faile in faith, and fall in transgression, by lying, stealing, &amp; oppressing, so as bloud touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth bloud, generall sinnes, will haue a generall iudgement, and when we are most secure, then will the Lord be most seuere; as it was in the daies of <hi>Noah,</hi> so shal the comming of the sonne of man be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Domestica mala maiora sunt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrimis,</hi> our home euills are grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then that they can be expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with teares: Protestants sinnes are Protestants staines, and worse then all that, we growe shameles, we dare to sinne with <hi>Absolon</hi> in<pb n="80" facs="tcp:176871:46"/>the sight of the sunne, no feare of God or man, no loue of vertue, no hatred of vice, no remorse of conscience, no danger of soule, no griefe of the spirit of God within vs, no horror of hell or death without vs, can restraine the violence of our affections, but sinne we will: surely, if there were no other signe in our <hi>Zodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack</hi> of a declining world, but our wofull declination from God, it were sufficiēt to warne vs. I might here shift from the sinnes, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther signes of the latter day, as warres, famine, plagues, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies.</p>
            <p>I might tel you that the Turks sword is drunke with the bloud of christians, I might tell you of a famine more general then vsuall, and of a greater dearth of all things, then euer yet this world
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:176871:46"/>felt, I might tell you of plagues depopulating the fairest coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries &amp; cities of the world, and so, <hi>Vt viui non sunt pares mortuis sepeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endis,</hi> as the liuing haue bin scarce enough to burie their dead. I might tell you of mōstrous births and prodigies. I might tel you of earth-quakes, Inundations, and fierie inflamations, all more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and fearefull, then former ages euer sawe, but I had rather keepe still my current, to tell of sinnes within vs, then of signes without vs, tolling on that feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day: Nor will I rancke them but out of the register of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, our discord within, cries vengeance without, and there is no poysoned shot to the nusl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d seedes of sedition, could the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens aboue endure the mutinie of Angels? or <hi>paradise</hi> belowe, the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:176871:47"/>groweth of two contrarie seedes? shall kingdomes then stand, if they be diuided? and shall the world abide thus distracted, sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie if euer, much more now, <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha</hi> his cōplaint is verified,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.5.</note>
               <hi>Trust ye not a friend, neither put ye cōfidēce in a counseller, keepe the doores of thy mouth from her that lyeth in thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, for the sonne reuileth the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the daughter riseth vp against her mother, the daughter in lawe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst her mother in lawe, &amp; a mans enemies are the men of his own house.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay more then all this, <hi>Diuulsa, sunt a se inuicem ecelesiae Christi membra,</hi> the members of Christ his Church are miserably rent, and torne, one from another, <hi>Ephraim</hi> against <hi>Manasses,</hi> and <hi>Manasses</hi> against <hi>Ephraim,</hi> both with open mouth, to deuoure poore <hi>Iuda.</hi> It was said of old, that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:176871:47"/>the warres of Infidels were the peace of Christians, but now the warres of Christians, are the peace of Infidels: and so to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this sinne, if discord be the fore runner of ruine, and not so much in regard of priuate state, as of the generall dissolution of all the world, I may safely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solue that the Lords approch is so much the neerer, by how much we are the more diuided.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> is yet more particular in his prophecie, of such sinnes, as should aboūd in the latter daies, which and if you either feele in your selues, or finde them in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, let them be like <hi>Baltasser,</hi> handwriting vpon your walles, threatning downe-right iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for new done sinnes.</p>
            <p>Into whose holy register if you looke you shall finde them
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:176871:48"/>thus digested,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 4.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 3.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 1. into sinnes of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postasie</hi> from the faith, 2. into sins of <hi>Rebellion</hi> against the faith.</p>
            <p>In the latter times the spirit speaketh euidently, that men shal depart from the faith, giue heed vnto spirits of error and doctrine of diuels, they shall speake lies through hipocrisie, and haue their conscience burned with an hote iron, forbidding to marrie, and commaunding to abstaine from meates, which God hath created to be receiued with gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of thankes, of them which beleeue and know the truth: was there euer in any age more fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from the faith, and sliding into error? did euer men speake lies with more hypocrisie? was conscience euer more branded? doctrines of diuels so diuulged? forbidding to marrie, and enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:176871:48"/>abstinēce frō meats, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God? if thus to faile in faith be an <hi>Apostasie</hi> from God, &amp; if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter such fals followeth iudgment, then is it nere, euen at our dores. Again, if (as the same Apos: saith) in the last day shal come perilous times, wherin mē shalbe louers of their owne selues, couetous, boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, proud, cursed speakers, diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bediēt to parēts, vnthākful, vnho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without natural affectiō, truce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breakers, false accusers, intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, fierce, dispisers of thē which are good, traytors, headie, high minded, louers of pleasure more thē louers of God, hauing a shew of godlines, but haue denied the power thereof: I say, if euen now the world be full of such rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons against the Lord, wee had neede to turne from such, least he be vpon vs ere wee be aware.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:176871:49"/>
            <p>And so for further search into this holie <hi>Register,</hi> looke and yee shall finde that <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iude</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in one,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude,</hi> 18. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.</note> that there should be mockers in the last time, which should walk after their owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlie lustes, makers of Sects, fleshlie, hauing not the spirit; now if the world be burdened with such a byrth, what can wee expect, but the time of its deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to be at hand?</p>
            <p>Lastlie,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Esdra.</hi> 8.15. 2 <hi>Eldr.</hi> 15.16.</note> I might tell you out of <hi>Esdras,</hi> of manie miseries and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, for them that shall liue in the latter time, that they shall walk in great pride, how the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple shall be seditious, not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their king, and the Princes should measure their right, by their might.</p>
            <p>I might tell you out of him, that the weaker the world is by
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:176871:49"/>reason of age,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Esdr.</hi> 14.16.</note> the more shall the euills be increased vppon them that dwell therein, that the world hath lost his youth, and the times begin to waxe olde, for the world is diuided into 12 parts,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vers.</hi> 9.</note> ten parts of it already are gone, and halfe of the tenth part, that <hi>Esau</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> struggle in the wombe of <hi>Sara,</hi> and <hi>Iacobs</hi> hand held fast the heele of <hi>Esau,</hi> intimating as hee saith,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Esdr.</hi> 6.8.9.</note> that <hi>Esau</hi> is the ende of this wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked world, and <hi>Iacob</hi> is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it that followeth. <hi>Sara</hi> is heauie of her byrth, and would be dis-burdened.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Musculus</hi> in his Epistle Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorie before the Psalmes, and written to the Senate &amp; Consull of <hi>Berna,</hi> sheweth the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishment of all these, and tells that they are past, come, &amp; gone, harbengers of the Lordes wrath,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:176871:50"/>and neere approach of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming: Adding further, that the impunitie of sin, is a signe of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent iudgement, in these wordes; <hi>Excrescunt omnis generis flagitia, id{que} multis in locis prorsus impune.</hi> Sinnes of all natures growe vp, and in most part of the world, go vnpunished.</p>
            <p>It was the subuersion of <hi>Ely</hi> his house, it will be the destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all the world. Further he saith, <hi>Non licet impune studere pieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, innocentiae, &amp; vt illa ait de deo nec male nec bene loqui conceditur,</hi> though sinne go vnpunished, yet righteousnes shall be afflicted in the latter day, when it shall not be safe, to speake either well or euill of God himselfe, to speake euill of God, will be thought diuellish, to speake well of God, wil be dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med too saintish.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:176871:50"/>
            <p>Thus to censure sinne and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, in the last day (euen in this our day) as the surest signe of our sauiours neere approch, I hope it will be no preiudice to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who sigh to see it, and grieue to feele it: and if any man thinke otherwise, and be contrarie min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he may put farre from him the euill day, and sleepe in his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, till the trumpet blowe, yet with this caution, that as se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure sinning hastned on the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of water, so will it doe of fire, &amp; with the floud of our wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, will rise the vengeance of our God, till it come fifteene cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits aboue the highest mountaine of <hi>Ararat,</hi> that is, til fire haue fined vs fit for our God, who will emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie all vpon his sommons, and fill all vpon his sentence, heauen with the saued, and hell with the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:176871:51"/>damned. And so to conclude this worlds dissolution with it trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression, sure I am, that all such as are sencelesse in sinning, shal be sensible in burning, as also that the sicke body, is nearest death when it hath no feeling of it maladie, the world is no lesse sicke then sencelesse, &amp; in a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Lathtrgie</hi> it feeleth no maladie: what hereafter may be I know not, he knoweth best who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all: but sure I am of this, that sinne was neuer more sinfull, shameles, nor sencelesse, the soūd thereof in this our Iron age, is I kethefall of <hi>Nilus, ad itla quae ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadupa nominentur,</hi> where falling from the steepe hilles to the owe bottomes, the inhabitants are dease with the cōtinuall fall ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: I say dease, in regard of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome, but apprehensiue enough
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:176871:51"/>of things lesse frequent. Or it is like the motion of the heauenlie <hi>Orbes,</hi> of so speedie a course, and high an harmonie, as <hi>Tully</hi> saith, <hi>Vt aures hominum capere non pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunt,</hi> that mens eares can not catch it.</p>
            <p>Woe is mee to tell, <hi>Hoc sonitu completae aures hominum absoraue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt:</hi> the drumme of sinne hath made deafe the eares of men, and like the people of <hi>Catadupa,</hi> wee heare anie fall but that of <hi>Nilus,</hi> wee apprehend anie sounde but that of sinne, so loude, so speedie, and so vsuall, as it whirleth about the whole world, senseles, either of the shower or shout of it invn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; the Lord diminish our sinnes, &amp; increase our Faith, so as our loue may abound yet more and more, in all knowledge, and in all feeling, that wee may allow
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:176871:52"/>those things that are best, that wee may be pure, and without offence, vntill the day of Christ, filled with the fruits of righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phillip.</hi> 1.9 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> which are by Iesus Christ, vnto the glorie and praise of God. Amen.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:176871:52"/>
            <head>THE DREAD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVLL DAY.</head>
            <head type="sub">The second Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Verse. 28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>So Christ was once offered to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the sinnes of many, and vnto them that looke for him, shall he appeare the second time without sinne vnto saluation.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He day of doome thus discouered, it now remaines, we come to the disso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution thereof, by Christ the worker of al our good, and the determiner of all our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils. In deliuerie wherof, it is with
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:176871:53"/>me as it was with <hi>Tymothius</hi> the Musitian, of whom it is said, that when he plaide before <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, he euer changed his tune, as he sawe the king affected. From the <hi>Ionick</hi> to the <hi>Lidian</hi> if he saw him dumpish, and from the <hi>Lidian</hi> to the <hi>Ionick</hi> harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, if he saw him too mirthfull. If such force was in Musick, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the kings heart, and to bring it within the compasse of his key and melodie, of how much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter power is the word of God, to raise vp the soules of his Saints, as we see them either deiected with too much iudgement, or embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened with too much mercy.</p>
            <p>When the law hath wounded, the Gospell must cure, and in the temper of both, must be our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredience, oyle and vinegar must be powred alike into the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:176871:53"/>man, least vinegar without oyle might too much corrode, or oyle without vinegar might make too supple: it may be the keene knife of incision hath lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted too deepe in your religious hearts, and that the day of doome like a dampe hath put out all the delights of pleasure, it may be the feare of fire, and combustion of this bad world, hath made you doubtfull of a better: it stands vs vpon therefore to helpe the mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die with a more gentle pultesse, to beate backe the dampe with a more glorious light, &amp; to quench the feare of fire with the Ocean of a greater mercy.</p>
            <p>And that is by Christ, whose painefull passion, as it hath can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled all our sinnes, in his first comming so theglorie of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection shall giue vs life, when
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:176871:54"/>he shall appeare the second time <hi>without sinne vnto saluation.</hi> In a word, Christ his owne &amp; alone sacrifice, hath taken away our sinne, death and doome, and to all that looke for him he shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare againe, tread vpon all, and lead captiuitie captiue.</p>
            <p>It is said of Christ in respect of his person, that he is fairer then the sonnes of men: and it may be likewise said of his offices, that in all excellencie, they are aboue the dignities of men, a Prophet more powerfull, then euer <hi>Moses</hi> was, a <hi>Priest</hi> more pleasing then euer <hi>Aaron</hi> was, and a <hi>King</hi> more puissant then euer <hi>Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chisedec</hi> was, for these are gone, but of his kingdome, prophecie, and priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, there is no end.</p>
            <p>So vrged by the holy Ghost, in the whole course of this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:176871:54"/>against the Iewish nation, who whilest he liued, maligned his person, and since his death hath persecuted his cause. Giue me leaue thē my deare brethren, to disswade you from such impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and as an abetter of the cause of Christ, yet further to build you on, that being rauished with the beautie of his brightnes, you may be enamored with the loue of his person, and so euer liue to loue him, who hath loued you, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen himselfe a sacrifice for the sinnes of all the world, and in whom now all things are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come anew, new heauen, new earth, new Prince, new Priest, new Altar, new sacrifice, new testament, new tabernacle, old things are passed away, <hi>Aaron</hi> is buried with his sinagogue, Law and all, in the bowels of Christ,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:176871:55"/>
               <hi>Michael</hi> our great Prince, stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for the children of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1.</note> &amp; <hi>Melchisedec</hi> our high Priest is priest to bleed, &amp; plead for the children, ô Lord, which thou hast giuen him.</p>
            <p>Now of this holy offering and sole sacrifice of Christ, for the saluatiō of our soules, once done by him, but often pleaded by vs, as the last issue of al our pleadings against sinne, hell, death, doome, and diuell, I am to speake if God will, and as the text shall guide me in that truth. Wherein first I doe obserue <hi>sufficiencie,</hi> to make the sacrifice more soueraigne, in that Christ by once suffering, tooke away the sinnes of many. The worlds perfection, grewe from one daies worke to sixe, and then came the Sabboth of rest, wherein the Lord sawe with so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:176871:55"/>the perfection of all his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. But in the blessed worke of our redemption, all was done at once, not many sufferings, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deaths, or many sacrifices, like <hi>Aaeans</hi> were required, for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, but one was sufficient to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie his father, &amp; saue his Saints: and therefore I may well say, as it is in my text, <hi>So Christ once suffered</hi> and it was sufficient.</p>
            <p>All things in Christ are abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and vniuersall, from whose sufficiencie to satisfie and saue, who detracteth any thing, is sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to a rufull raze: who addeth any thing as of his owne, is in danger of a cursse, with an exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration.</p>
            <p>I say, he is all sufficiēt in name, nature, and office, his name is <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus,</hi> and that sufficient to saue: his nature is <hi>Emanuel,</hi> God with vs,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:176871:56"/>God in vs, and God for vs, all sufficient in himselfe, all sufficient for vs, we need none other. And for his offices wherein is he defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, as a <hi>Prophet</hi> he instructeth our soules, as a King, he conquers our enemies: and as a <hi>Priest,</hi> he pleaseth our God, and none but he, of whom the Father said, <hi>This is my welbeloued sonne, in whom I am well pleased, heare him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Saint at <hi>Sychar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.5.</note> run to the citie, and said; <hi>Come see a man that hath told me all that euer I did,</hi> is not he that Christ? so may I say, come see a man that hath vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done all the euil that euer we did, and is not he a Sauiour? by our first fall we lost our place, we dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased our God, &amp; wee brought vpon vs and ours, a curse with corruption, but he hath recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red our losses, repaired our ruins,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:176871:56"/>pleased our God, and conferred vpon vs and our children a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing with eternitie.</p>
            <p>If any man say I haue done it for him, let him be the vnitie, and if any dare say, I haue done it with him, let him be of the trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: if not, be silent ô heauens, and thou earth say nothing: ô men be ye mute, Angels hush, and ye fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Cherubines couer your faces, ere ye presume to flie before him. Its not one of you in particular, nor all in generall, that are suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to purge our sinnes, plead our cause, or purchase our place.</p>
            <p>The Prophetesse hath concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and borne a sonne,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esay.</hi> 8.3.</note>
               <hi>Maher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shalalhash-ban</hi> is his name: that is, make speed to the spoile, hast to the prey. Its he that hath taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the riches of <hi>Damascus,</hi> and the spoile of <hi>Samaria,</hi> before the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:176871:57"/>king of <hi>Ashur.</hi> It is he that hath led captiuitie captiue, &amp; giuen gifts, euen remission of all our sinnes, and euerlasting life, to the which God bring vs. It is the Lord all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufficient, who alone of all the world, &amp; none other, hath fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the lawe, satisfied for sinne, broken the sting of death, and conquered hell: it is he that hath subdued all by the might of his power, and redeemed all in the depth of his mercies, the serpent stung vs, and none could kill the venome, or expel the poyson, but the blood of the Physition: no pultesse, no playster, no cunning, no craft, no art of the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, no Fullers sope, could worke or wash out the staines of sinne, but the alone blood of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: no gold, no siluer, no merit of Saint, or might of Angell, could
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:176871:57"/>beg, or buye out our bondage, but it must be the deare death of the Redeemer.</p>
            <p>Our aduersaries haue endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered themselues in ramming vp the perfect, pleasing, and perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all sacrifice of Christ his death, once offered for all, by their day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sacrificing in their masse, as if his alone suffering once for all vpon the crosse, were not suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient without iteration, which were an argument of it imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Againe, haue they not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached the honour of their Christ, as insufficiēt to saue, when they make his mercy not suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent without their merit, his grace not sufficiēt without their works, his free pardon not sufficient, without their deare indulgence? his true and tried word not suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, without their tyring tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:176871:58"/>his sacraments not suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent without their additions of oile, creame, and spittle, in the one, and of Pix, print, and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cring in the other: his Sabbaoths not sufficient, without their farre fetched festiualls and ferialls, his heauen not sufficient without their hellish purgatorie, his medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation not sufficient without their intercession of Saints, &amp; Angels. Nay more then all that went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and I yearne to speake it, his blood not sufficient, without the blood of <hi>Hales,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In a Primer of Salisbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vse prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Paris. 1532.</note> and <hi>Becket,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that, <hi>Tu per Thomae sangi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem quem parte impendit, fac nos christe scandere quo Thomas ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</hi> Thou by the blood of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> which for thee he did spend: make vs ô Christ thither to clime where <hi>Thomas</hi> did ascend.</p>
            <p>But good Lord, how long wilt
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:176871:58"/>thou endure such indignitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thy Christ? how long shall they thus and thus spit in his face, nip his cheekes, beate his body, curse his soule, &amp; trample vnder foote the blood of his couenant? Surely, surely, this people haue committed two sinnes, they haue forsaken thee, the fountaine of liuing water, and digged vnto themselues cesternes, euen bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken cesternes, which will hold no water.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sampson</hi> in his daliance with <hi>Dalilah,</hi> lost but the haire of his head, they in their spirituall daly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance (as they tearme it) haue cut off, not onely haire, but head and all. There was no smith found in all the land of <hi>Israel,</hi> for the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listines</hi> said, lest the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> make them swords, or speares. So our aduersaries, whilest they robbe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:176871:59"/>vs of our Christ,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.19.</note> haue taken from vs all meanes of munition, and leaue vs no toole to worke with, but of their owne sharpning.</p>
            <p>They deale with vs, as <hi>Ier oboam</hi> the sonne of <hi>Nebot</hi> did, which caused <hi>Israel</hi> to sinne, and said it is too farre to goe to <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> it is sufficient to stay here at <hi>Dan,</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> there is a calfe at <hi>Dan,</hi> and a calfe at <hi>Bethel,</hi> with an holy day to the Lord, a cake at <hi>Dan,</hi> &amp; a cake at <hi>Bethel</hi> with an holy day to the Lord: But good Lord how long shall they waine vs frō the pretious blood of our Christ as insufficient, and fill vs with the winde of their vaine imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? how long shall they dimme the gold of thy sanctuarie, and robbe thee of thine honour?</p>
            <p>They haue left vnto thee, the wretched crowne of thornes, &amp; taken to themselues the diademe
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:176871:59"/>of worldly honour: they haue put into thy hands an hollow reed, and taken to themselues, the Imperiall scepter: they haue left thee poorly ryding vpon an asse, and painfully hanging vpon the tree, whilest themselues in their papall pride, do iustifie their <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sian</hi> pompe, ride vpō their tamed and trapped steeds, and hang vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the shoulders of men.</p>
            <p>And yet as if all this were not sufficiēt to set vp themselues, and to pull thee downe as insufficiēt, they haue dimmed the glorious light of thy word, derned thy prophecy, with <hi>Romish</hi> iustitutiōs, <hi>Decretals</hi> apostaticall, lying <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Illusions,</hi> &amp; flattering <hi>Diuina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> but good Lord how long?</p>
            <p>Finally, for the honour of thy Priest-hood, how haue they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuated the vertue therof, as not sufficient, either to sacrifice, or to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:176871:60"/>be sacrificed once for all, with out their iteration of a daily masse, in their missall, with an vsurped au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of <hi>Melchisecks</hi> order, which is so proper to Christ, as it cannot passe from one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the words in the originall will so beare it:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.24.</note>
               <hi>This man because he endureth euer, hath a Priest-hood which cannot passe from one to an other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I doe secondly obserue in this once offering of Christ to make it the more soueraigne, <hi>vniuersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,</hi> where it is said to take away the sinnes of many: and in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, the blood of Christ doth clense vs frō all our sinnes: and againe, he is the propitiation for our sins, &amp; not for ours only, but for the sins of al the world: to teach vs, <hi>y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
               </hi> al the promises of God run vpon an vniuersall grace of
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:176871:60"/>fered to all, though receiued of fewe, according to that, <hi>Omnia in christo sunt noua, categorica, &amp; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholica.</hi> All things in Christ are new, absolute, &amp; vniuersall, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises in the scriptures run vpon an vniuersall grace offered; As, <hi>Come vnto me all, &amp;c. He gaue his onely begotten sonne, that all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued in him, &amp;c.</hi> Yet euer with limitation of cōming, beleeuing, and looking for him, that should appeare the second time.</p>
            <p>And here a little examine the words, and see the effectuall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Christ his death, in this his sole sacrifice, which is, as you here see, to take away the sinnes of many.</p>
            <p>He tooke to himselfe no king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, crownes, or dignities of this world, but crosse, curse, and crueltie, to heale our maladie. A
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:176871:61"/>different death, of his &amp; ours, for our death is the reward of sinne: his death is the ruine of sinne: our death doth credit it, his death doth cure it; he died that did no sinne, to take away the sinnes of many: we die, who neuer did wel to take away the righteousnes of one: ô soueraigne death, &amp; sweet sacrifice, that tooke away, not the sins of one among all, or of some few among many, but it tooke away the sins of all, who sought into his death for life, &amp; searched into his wounds as <hi>Thomas</hi> did.</p>
            <p>No age, no condition of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, no sexe, but either of all sorts some, or many among all, haue benefited so much as the salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their soules commeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, by the death of their deliuerer: yea I may safely say with the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Apostle, that through peace
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:176871:61"/>made by that blood, of that his crosse,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Colloss.</hi> 1.20.</note> it pleased God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile to himselfe, through him, all things which are both in earth, and which are in heauen, a sacrifice so soueraigne, as you may there see, that not onely the Saints haue longed for it, but the very Angels haue desired to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it, being the cōfirmation of their high &amp; angelicall state, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by so established, as now they shall neuer fall againe.</p>
            <p>Lastly, soueraigne in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, that it left no staine behind, but tooke away the sinnes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: and (as I may say) quit vs of all transgression. And if any man aske how I answere by curing, couering, not imputing, and forgetting: as and if he should say, that sinne which I cannot cure, I will couer: that which I can neither cure nor couer,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:176871:62"/>I will not impute, that which I can, neither cure, couer, nor but impute, I will forget, and this is the free forgiuenes of sinne, and pardon of our offēces done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meede or merit of any,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esay.</hi> 63.1.</note> but of him who spake in righteousnes, and is mightie to saue.</p>
            <p>I doe further obserue to make this sacrifice more soueraigne, a facilitie in vs, to apprehend so great a benefit onely applied by faith, in looking, &amp; longing after Christ, his glorious appearing. For so it is here said vnto thē that looke for him, he shall appeare the second time without sinne vnto saluation.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Kings.</hi> 5, 10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> should be healed of his leprosie, <hi>Elisha</hi> sent a messenger vnto him saying, goe and wash thee in <hi>Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> seauen times, and thou shalt
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:176871:62"/>be cleansed, but <hi>Naaman</hi> was wroth, and went away, saying: Are not <hi>Abanah</hi> and <hi>Phatpat,</hi> ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of <hi>Damascus,</hi> better then all the waters of <hi>Israel?</hi> But his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants came and saide, Father, if the Prophet had cōmanded thee a great thing, wouldest thou not haue done it? How much rather then, when he saide to thee, <hi>Wash and be cleane.</hi> The Leprosie of <hi>Naaman</hi> cleaueth vnto vs, sinne hath seazed vppon all flesh, and ther's no washing can clēse it, but the bloud of our Christ, which to apprehend by faith, looking, and longing after it, is the meane of our clensing, be it farre from anie to value those Springs, with the waters of <hi>Damascus:</hi> Nor is it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great thing (as it is in my text) to looke, and be saued, to wash and be clensed, all done by faith,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:176871:63"/>which apprehends Christ Iesus, with all the benefites of his pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, which is remission of sinnes, and euerlasting life, to the which, God bring vs.</p>
            <p>So then I say, for the surer seale and certainty of this our clensing by Christ his bloud, our soules are filled with the sweetnes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, &amp; all is thus conueied vnto vs. 1. <hi>Verbo. quo offertur. 2. Fide, qua recipitur. 3. Spirita, quo applicatur.</hi> 4. <hi>Sacramento, quo consignatur.</hi> The word of God, it offers this grace: the hand of Faith, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues this grace: the spirit of Truth, it applyes this grace: and the holie Sacrament, confirmes this grace: and thus are we assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of our daily clensing, and the bloud of Christ is yet sprinkling, and fresh bleeding, to all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:176871:63"/>
            <p>Yet as you see with this cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that we look &amp; long for his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cōming, otherwise it is but a defeizāce of all the good that he hath purchased, for though grace preuēting, grace assisting, &amp; grace perfecting be al his, &amp; none ours; yet we must by Faith apprehend that grace, ere euer wee can be crowned with glory: for true it is, <hi>Qui fecit te, non saluabit te, sine te,</hi> he that made thee, without thee, wil neuer saue thee without thee: aske, and haue, seeke, and ye shall finde, knocke, and it shall be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, looke for him, and hee will appear vnto your saluation. I loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked (saith <hi>Iohn) and loe a Lambe stood vpon mount Syon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 14.1.</note> he saw no Lambe till hee looked, and he lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp his eyes, before hee sawe the mountaine of his holinesse: I lifte mine eyes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 121.</note> (saith <hi>Dauid</hi>)
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:176871:64"/>vnto the hills, and my helpe came from the Lord: his eyes were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, ere he gained any help be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hos.</hi> 12.4.</note> And it is saide of <hi>Iacob,</hi> that hee wept and prayed, and found God at <hi>Bethel,</hi> he found him not, till he sought him in prayers and teares.</p>
            <p>And heere I would obserue a difference betwixt the godly and the wicked of this world, in their different lookes, much looking in this world, little longing after another: one looks vpon his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, wealth and witte: another, vpon his wife, children, and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants: one lookes vpon his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure: another vpon his profites: but who looketh towardes him that shall appeare the secōd time, without sinne vnto Saluation? one seeth his sin, &amp; is sencelesse: another seeth his death, &amp; is des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate:
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:176871:64"/>both loathe the daye of Christ his cōming, they neither looke nor long after the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their bodies, the reason is, they haue no Faith. For as it is true, how can they call on him, of whom they haue not heard? so is it as true, how can they looke or long for him, on whome they haue not belieued? <hi>Abraham</hi> was glad to see my day (saith Christ) hee looked and longed for him: so did <hi>Symeon, Elizabeth, Anna,</hi> and <hi>Zacharie:</hi> they looked after the consolation of <hi>Israel,</hi> they lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged after grace, that they might come to glorie. So haue the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of God euer done, they haue longed after the redemption of their bodies, and they desired to see the Sonne of God comming in the cloudes, whereas the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked stand in dread of that gloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:176871:65"/>day, and looke for the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to fall vpon them.</p>
            <p>O well,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esay.</hi> 30.18.</note> said the Prophet; <hi>The Lord is the God of iudgement, blessed are all they that waite for him.</hi> And <hi>Paul,</hi> after hee had wept ouer the damned crue of his dayes, when he came to mention the memory of Gods Saintes on earth, he said with solace,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20.</note> to his saued soule, <hi>But our consolation is in heauen, whence also wee looke for the Sauiour, euen the Lord Iesus Christ, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter</hi> is much more speedie in the expectāce of <hi>Christ</hi> his second comming:
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12.</note> who after he had told to the terror of the wicked, that there was <hi>Dies, &amp; Deus vitionis,</hi> a God, and a day of reuenge, in which the heauens should passe away with a noyse, and the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments should melte with heate, and the Earth, with the workes
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:176871:65"/>that are therein, should be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp: seeing (saith hee) that all these things must be dissolued, what manner persons ought wee to be in holie conuersation and godlinesse; looking for, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting vnto the comming of that day of God, by the which, the heauens being on fire, shall be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued, and the Elements shall melt with heate, but we looke for newe heauens, and a new earth, according to his promise, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in dwelleth righteousnes, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To incourage the Saints at <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.7.</note> that they are not destitute of anie gifts, hee tells them they are wanting of none, in that they are euer wayting for <hi>y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
               </hi> appearing of our Lord Iesus Christ. If then he that wayreth, is destitute of no good gift, surely, hee that neuer loketh therafter, is destitute of all.</p>
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:176871:66"/>
            <p>Lastlie, after that <hi>Paule</hi> had told <hi>Titus,</hi> that the grace of God that bringeth saluation to all men had appeared, and taught, that wee should denie vngodlinesse, and worldly lusts, that we should liue soberlie and righteouslie,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Titus</hi> 13.</note> and godlily in this present world, at last shutteth vp all, with the loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for of that blessed hope, and appearing of that glorie, of that mightie God, and Sauiour Iesus Christ.</p>
            <p>And so for vse of this doctrine, and to close with your religious eares and hearts, which heare me this day: Surely, surely, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded, ther was neuer age, lesse mindful of the comming of their Christ to iudgement, or lesse de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous of the day of his appearāce in glorie, <hi>Cupio dissolui,</hi> is far from this dissolute age: and who with
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:176871:66"/>the liuely &amp; louely Hart, breathes after the wells of those sweet wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? I meane the fresh springs of glory. For who wayteth, who looketh, who hasteth vnto the comming of that day of God?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.63.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Isaac</hi> toward the euening went out to pray in the fielde, he lift vp his eyes and looked, and behold, the Cammels came: hee gained <hi>Rebecca,</hi> by praying for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishment of that he looked and longed after: the mariage of the Lambe is come, and his wife hath made her selfe readie, readie with Lampe and Oyle,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Thess.</hi> 4.17.</note> to meete him in the cloudes, and to be caught vp to meete the Lord in the aire, and so euer be with him. Bretheren, comfort your selues one another, with these words.</p>
            <p>I do further obserue the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit we receiue by the sole sacrifice
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:176871:67"/>of Christ, which is saluation to such that looke for him, with no sin in himself: for so saith the text, <hi>he shall come without sinne,</hi> without sin in himself, that is, without the iudgement of our sinnes, which gat hold vpon him, in the daies of his life, &amp; at the hour of his death.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Without sinne, in his Saintes, sufficientlie purged with that his bloud, pleading their cause, and purchasing their place.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And yet behold a greater mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie, I may lay without sinne, in the damned, when all their sinnes shall be turned to shame, and all their wickednes into iudgement, the act of sinning, in some sort shall cease, but the act of burning shal neuer cease: the damned shal die, for all they haue done, and be neuer doing, but euer dying, as <hi>Patients</hi> in the paine they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:176871:67"/>by their sinnes, at so deare a price, paine, and passion shall cease the sinne, but increase the iudgement; lust and lucre shall then languish, but the worme shall neuer die.</p>
            <p>So now, for vse of all that hath bene said, it may easilie be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that Christ hath a double comming, one in grace, and thats his first cōming; another in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, &amp; thats his second comming.</p>
            <p>In his first comming, he appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in all humility: in the second, hee shall appeare in all Maiestie. In the first, he came in the forme of a Seruant to all; in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, he shall appeare as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder of all. In the first, hee came to be iudged of the world: in the second, hee shall come to iudge the world. In his first comming, his voyce
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:176871:68"/>was not heard, and he fell downe like a showre of Raine, vpon a fleece of Wooll, but his second comming shall be with a shoute, for the dead shall heare his voice, and the graues shall be opened: at his first comming, his Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie was silent, and his humanitie did speak: but at his second com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, his humanitie shall be si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, &amp; his Diuinitie shall speake. When he first came, none would belieue his report, but when hee shall come againe, euery eye shall see him, and euerie tongue shall say, This is hee, whome I haue pierced. In a word, when he first came, hee came to suffer hunger, colde, sinne, shame, lawe, diuell, and death, but when hee cōmeth againe, hee shall tread vpon all these, with a glorious tryumph: hee shall leade captiuitie captiue,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:176871:68"/>giue giftes vnto men, saluation to his Elect, Iudgement to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, and glory to his Father.</p>
            <p>All this, must his Elect see, as <hi>Peter</hi> sawe it, when hee saide, Of the which saluation the Prophets haue enquired and searched, which Prophecied of the grace that should come to vs: searching when, or at what time the spirit, which testified before of Christ, which was in them, shuld declare the sufferings that should come vnto Christ, and the glorie that should followe, see then, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold your King, not crowned with thorns and reproach, ready to be iudged for all: but looke vpon him with his crowne of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding glorie at hand, to iudge all.</p>
            <p>Againe, I doe obserue out of the text, that as Christ had a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:176871:69"/>cōming, one in grace, &amp; an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in glorie: so hath he perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a double sacrifice, &amp; satisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō to <hi>God,</hi> for the sins of our souls</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Vpon his first comming, which was the day of grace to vs, but of miserie to him, he pleaded <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter,</hi> in such obedience as apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, perfecting in our flesh, the full accomplishment of the lawe of God, as well by internall, as externall obedience.</p>
            <p>Againe, hee pleaded for vs, <hi>passibiliter,</hi> passiuely; whilest hee suffered and endured for vs, both the torture of crosse &amp; consciēce, bearing vpon his blessed bodie, and sauing soule, all the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of all our sinnes, his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent &amp; passiue intercession, made for vs by him, who made all, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the oblation, enlarged it self to all, in that it was offered for
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:176871:69"/>all, as also, in respect of sufficiēcy, it might serue for all, being suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciēt for all the world, <hi>Si modo cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret,</hi> if it could belieue; How be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, <hi>Virtualiter, siue energeticos:</hi> that is, in vertue, power, &amp; efficacie, it reacheth onely the faithful belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. For so long as wee liue in the kingdome of grace, &amp; so long as the nūber of the saued is vnac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished, so long the vertue of Christ his death worketh, &amp; is ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall, applied by faith, to bring men to <hi>Christ,</hi> frō grace, to glorie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But vpon his second comming, Christ shall be glorious, not bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Crosse, shame, and smart of sin, but he shall come raigning, ruling, triumphing, and exalted aboue the height of all sublimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Then will he pleade for vs, <hi>Collocatiue, &amp; fruitiue,</hi> hee will gather vs from all Nations vnder
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:176871:70"/>heauen, hee will place vs in the reall possession of his celestiall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, and hee will giue vs to enioy full fruition of perfect bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sednes.</p>
            <p>And as if hee should say: Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, here am I, with the children whom thou hast giuen me, I gaue my soule a sacrifice for their sins, let it be thy pleasure to giue them a kingdome; For what is it, that I haue gathered them out of a bad world, if I may not place them in a better? What is it to place thē in a better, if they may not enioy all the delights theros? O Father, I tooke their sinne for a time, let mee now betake them to thee for euer.</p>
            <p>Lastly, it may be here doubted and demaunded, what the spirit meaneth by this, that Christ shall come the second time, without sinne<gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176871:70"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>